Guide to the Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers TAM.694
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers
1956-2016
1946-2018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Schneier, Arthur, Rabbi
TAM.694
96.5 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 188 manuscript boxes, 12 half manuscript boxes, 6 small flat boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, and 5 media boxes.
39 audiocassettes
7 film reels
6 VHS
119.40 Gigabytes in 15,417 computer files.
The Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers consists of materials created and collected by Rabbi Arthur Schneier over the course of his life as a rabbi and advocate for human rights. The material in the collection dates from 1942 to 2018 with the bulk of the material spanning from the 1970s to the mid 2010s. The content of the collection centers around Schneier's work as an internationally known rabbi and as the president of the Appeal of Conscience Foundation. The bulk of the material present in this collection includes: correspondence, photographs, images, press, clippings, memoranda, and ephemera from various domestic and international events. The collection also contains a small amount of audiovisual material the bulk of which is audio cassette tapes containing recordings of various Appeal of Conscience Foundation events and conferences attended by the rabbi.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Rabbi Arthur Schneier in 2017 and 2019. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2017.035, 2017.067, 2017.075, and 2019.011.
Arrangement
The material in this collection mostly follows the original order of the inventory supplied by Rabbi Arthur Schneier and maintained by Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives. The arrangement of the collection reflects the groupings by subject matter from Rabbi Schneier's inventory. The arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Appeal of Conscience Foundation Material, 1964-2018, undated
Subseries I.A. Annual Seminar on Foreign and Religious Life for the Foreign Service Institute, 1981-2012, undated
Subseries I.B. Annual Awards Dinners and Luncheons, 1969-2018, undated
Subseries I.C. Appeal of Conscience Foundation Delegations to Foreign Countries, 1966-2012, undated
Subseries I.D. International Political and Religious Leaders Hosted by Appeal of Conscience Foundation, 1968-2014, undated
Subseries I.E. Peace and Tolerance Conferences, 1991-2005, undated
Subseries I.F. Correspondence, 1964-2016, undated
Series II. International and Domestic Events, 1956-2016, undated
Subseries II.A. Conferences, Summits, and Forums, 1956-2015, undated
Subseries II.B. Commemorative Events, 1976-2016, undated
Subseries II.C. Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1976-2011, undated
Series III. Memberships and Affiliations, 1956-2014, undated
Series IV. Rabbi of Congregation B'nai Jacob and Park East Synagogue Records, 1942-2016, undated
Biographical Note
Rabbi Arthur Schneier (1930- ) was born on March 20, 1930 in Vienna, Austria, and lived under Nazi occupation in Budapest until age 17. Schneier immigrated to the United States in 1947. He graduated with a Bachelor of Arts from Yeshiva University in 1951 and earned a Masters of Arts from New York University in 1953. In 1955, Schneier received his rabbinical ordination from Yeshiva University. Schneier became the Senior Rabbi at Park East Synagogue in 1962. As of 2019, Schneier continues to serve as the Senior Rabbi of Park East Synagogue. Before coming to Park East Synagogue, Schneier served as the rabbi of Congregation B'nai Jacob in Brooklyn, New York. In 1975, Rabbi Arthur Schneier founded the Park East Day School.
Over the years, Rabbi Arthur Schneier has been an active member of many prominent religious and political organizations including: the Council on Foreign Relations, United Nations Development Corporation, United Nations Alliance of Civilizations, and the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum Committee. Schneier founded the Appeal of Conscience Foundation in 1965 and has served as the president of the Foundation since its inception. The Appeal of Conscience Foundation brings together business and religious leaders to promote peace and tolerance internationally and domestically.
Scope and Contents
The Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers consists of material collected and created by Rabbi Arthur Schneier dating from 1956 to 2016 pertaining to his work as a rabbi and international advocate for peace, human rights, and religious freedom. The bulk of the collection documents Schneier's work as the president and founder of the Appeal of Conscience Foundation, or ACF, an interfaith coalition of business and religious leaders promoting tolerance and conflict resolution throughout the world. ACF created and co-sponsored protests, seminars, conferences, summits, and awards about creating international peace and tolerance through conflict resolution and the expansion of human and religious rights. Material from these events include: programs, correspondence, schedules, lists of attendees, agendas, press clippings and releases, photographs, images, video recordings, and travel documents. A small number of VHS tapes, microcassette tapes, and audio cassette tapes were recorded of ACF's annual award dinners and luncheons as well as the seminars and conferences co-sponsored and created by ACF. ACF also hosted visiting political and religious leaders of international renown and sent delegations abroad to report to meet with international political and religious leaders. The collection mostly contains paper-based and born-digital material, with a small portion of audio cassette tapes documenting those meetings.
Rabbi Arthur Schneier also attended several domestic and international events as individual advocate for religious tolerance and international peace. A large portion of the collection documents Schneier's constant trips to Israel, Europe, and East Asia to attend international events about religious and human rights. Material from Schneier's trips includes: itineraries, schedules, correspondence, photographs, travel documents and ephemera, and reports. A small number of audio cassette tapes and 16mm films were recorded from various international and domestic events attended by Rabbi Schneier as an advocate for religious rights. Another small part of the collection consists of photographs, images, programs, correspondence, born-digital sound and video recordings that record Rabbi Schneier receiving awards and honorary doctorate degrees for his vocational work as a rabbi and advocate. Finally, this collection contains material that documents Schneier's vocation as a rabbi first as the Rabbi of Congregation B'nai Jacob located in Brooklyn, New York then as the Senior Rabbi of Park East Synagogue in New York, New York.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Appraisal
During accessioning, the curator was able to weed out most of the boxes that contained administrative and/or financial files. However, there were some administrative files embedded within certain boxes, especially the ones that focus on the Annual Award Dinners which were weeded during processing. Additionally, there were several boxes full of unannotated envelopes, invitation and RSVP cards for the Appeal of Conscience Foundation's Annual Awards Dinner. Two copies of the invitations and RSVP cards were retained, the rest of the material was deaccessioned. There were some boxes that contained receipts, tax return forms, tax audit correspondence, reimbursement documents, and a financial investment portfolio for the United States-Japan Foundation that were deaccessioned from the collection. There were several folders of articles, booklets, pamphlets, and reports about international countries which were not created by the Appeal of Conscience Foundation that had little to no research value which were also deaccessioned. In the same vein as the articles, booklets, pamphlets, and reports, the donor also kept folders of speeches by world leaders from various conferences, summits, forum, news conferences that are not annotated which were also discarded. There were two yarmulkes, housed in boxes 108 and 183, that were offered back to the donor and deaccessioned.
After consulting with the digital archivist, six data cartridges were separated from the collection, offered back to the donor, and deaccessioned. These cartridges were labeled as backup files and are currently unable to be imaged by NYU. The digital archivist said they will need to be sent to a vendor and probably do not contain information of high research value. There were a number of optical discs and floppy disks which blank, damaged, or had copyright issues that were deaccessioned from the collection. Please see the deaccessioning checklist in the collection file for a detailed list of optical disc and floppy disk deaccessions.
Two audio cassette tapes were removed from the collection due to copyright issues. Fifteen audio cassette tapes were also removed from the collection, because they were blank. One 16mm film was removed from the collection due to copyright issues.
Electronic Records Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Custodial History
All of the materials in this collection were stored either at the Appeal of Conscience office on 251 West 71st street or at the Park East Synagogue at 163 East 67th street. Material was packed by Rabbi Arthur Schneier and his daughter, Karen Schneier.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection.
United States -- Foreign relations.; China; Jews -- Soviet Union; Religion and social problems.; Politics and culture.; Faxes.; Clippings files.; International relations.; Romania.; Soviet Union.; Austria.; Judaism.; Holocaust survivors.; Jewish refugees |z Hungary.; Video recordings.; Audiocassettes.; Digital images.; Color photographs.; Menus
- Series I. Appeal of Conscience Foundation Material, 1964-2018, undated; 29 audiocassettes; 5 VHS; 52.75 Gigabytes in 6,985 computer files.; 32 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 59 manuscript boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 2.5 small flat boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 2.5 media boxes.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material collected and created by ACF from 1964 to 2018. This series includes programs, slides, travel documents, itineraries, agendas, schedules, speech transcripts, correspondence, photographs, press, images, audio and video recordings, and ephemera from ACF related events, meetings, and trips. The bulk of the material consists of correspondence created by ACF to inform their donor base about events and activities co-sponsored and created by the Foundation. Included in ACF correspondence are the Foundation's newsletter and correspondence with internationally renowned political and religious dignitaries. Also present in this series are an annual seminar that the Foundation runs for the United States Department of State, and an annual awards dinner and luncheon that serves as the major fundraiser for the Foundation. Since its inception, ACF has hosted many religious and political dignitaries domestically and has also sent many interfaith delegations abroad to promote religious tolerance. This series contains audio recordings, speeches, photographs, press, agendas, schedules, travel documents, and correspondence from all activities related to those types of trips and meetings. There is a small amount of material in this series documenting ACF delegations visiting the Soviet Union to advocate for Soviet Jews throughout the 1970s. There are some brochures, audio recordings, agendas, folders, notes, copies of resolutions, correspondence, and press related material from the international Peace and Tolerance Conferences that ACF co-sponsored and co-ran with the Orthodox Patriarche from 1992-2005.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into the following subseries:
  I.A. Annual Seminar on Foreign and Religious Life for the Foreign Service Institute, 1981-2012, undated
  I.B. Annual Awards Dinners and Luncheons, 1969-2018, undated
  I.C. Appeal of Conscience Foundation Delegations to International Countries, 1966-2012, undated
  I.D. International Political and Religious Leaders Hosted by Appeal of Conscience Foundation, 1968-2014, undated
  I.E. Peace and Tolerance Conferences, 1991-2005, undated
  I.F. Correspondence, 1964-2016, undated
  - Subseries I.A. Annual Seminar on Foreign and Religious Life for the Foreign Service Institute, 1981-2012, undated; 5 audiocassettes; 3 VHS; 24.70 Gigabytes in 471 computer files.; 3.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 3.5 manuscript boxes, and .25 media box.
    This subseries contains ephemera from the annual seminar that Appeal of Conscience Foundation runs for the State Department's foreign service officers before the officers receive their overseas assignments. The seminar takes place at the Foreign Service Institute, or FSI, and the material in this subseries dates back to 1981. Material in this subseries includes: copies of lectures, photographs, correspondence, information packets, brochures, programs, articles, schedules, images, audio cassette tapes, VHS tapes, video recordings, and filled out questionnaires. There are some born-digital media--images and video--in this subseries.
    Material in this subseries is grouped chronologically by year, then arranged alphabetically by type.
    - 1981 FSI Seminar: Briefing Session Materials, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1982 FSI Seminar: Information Packet, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1983 FSI Seminar: Information Packet, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1984 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1984 FSI Seminar: Information Packet, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1985 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 11, 12)
    - 1985 FSI Seminar: Speeches, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 277, Folder 42)
    - 1986 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1985-1986; 3 folders (Box 1, Folder 13, Box 207, Folder 21, Box 160, Folder 10)
    - 1986 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Speech -- Mahoney, Sister Colette, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Attendees and Schedules, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 18, Box 207, Folder 20)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Sample Letters, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- China, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Bulgaria, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Czechoslovakia, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Hungary, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Poland, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Romania, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Soviet Union, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Yugoslavia, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Material Distributed -- Map, Booklets, and Printout, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1987 FSI Seminar: Program and List of Participants, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1988 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 207, Folder 19, Box 215, Folder 7)
    - 1988 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Information Packet Inserts -- China, Romania, Hungary, USSR, Bulgaria, Poland and Czechoslovakia, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 32, 33)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Literature Distributed, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Notes, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Notes -- Levi, Rabbi, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - 1989 FSI Seminar: Photographs and Negatives, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1990 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 207, Folder 17)
    - 1990 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, Expenses, and List of Participants, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - 1990 FSI Seminar: Information Packets and Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - 1990 FSI Seminar: Information Packets and Distributed Materials, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 37, 38)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Articles, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Biographical File -- Kishkovsky, Father Leonid, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Foreign Service Institute, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitations, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Speech, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: List of Participants, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: List of Participants and Notes, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Literature Distributed, 1984-1990; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 43, 44)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Notes, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Sign -- Bulgaria Salon H, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - 1991 FSI Seminar: Sound Recordings (Box 206, Cassette 694.0005, 694.0006)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Handouts, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 27, 28)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Information Packet, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Notes, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1992 FSI Seminar: Sound Recordings, 1992, undated (Box 206, Cassette 694.0007, 694.0008)
    - 1993 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 207, Folder 18)
    - 1993 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, Notes, and Lists of Participants, 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 31, 32)
    - 1993 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Albania, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - 1993 FSI Seminar: Notes and Programs, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 1993 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Articles, 1977-1994; 4 folders (Box 2, Folder 11, 13-15)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Foreign Service Institute, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitation, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Speakers, 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 18, 19)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Photographs -- Post-Seminar, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Handouts, 1977-1984; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Brooks, David, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Schneier, Rabbi Arthur, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Lists of Participants, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Notes, undated; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 17, 20)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1994 FSI Seminar: Programs, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Foreign Service Institute, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitations, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Speakers, 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 36-38)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Thank You Letters to Participants, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Handouts, 1984-1995; 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 44-46)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Albania, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Lists of Participants, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Photographs and Negatives, 1995, undated; 1 folder (Box 128, Folder 3)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionnaires, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Programs, Notes, and Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1995 FSI Seminar: Syllabi -- Foreign Service Institute Area Studies, undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Foreign Service Institute, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitations and Requests to Speakers for Biographical Information, 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 5, 6)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Thank You Letters, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Handouts, undated; 4 folders (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Information Packet --Baltic States, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Notes and Programs, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1996 FSI Seminar: Programs, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Foreign Service Institute, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitations to Students, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Speakers' Biographical Information, 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 3, 4)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Thank You Letter to Appeal of Conscience Foundation, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes -- Invitations, undated; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes -- Possible Speakers, undated; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, Notes, Speeches, and Biographical Information -- Keynote Speaker, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Russia, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Lists of Sessions Speakers and Topics, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1997 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Fundraising, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Speakers, 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 19, 20)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence and Notes -- Foreign Service Institute, 1997-1998; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Correspondence, Speeches, and Biographical Information -- Keynote Speaker, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Information Packet -- Russia, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Post-Seminar Questionaires, 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 17, 18)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: Program, List of Participants, and Name Tag, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1998 FSI Seminar: United States Policy Reports, 1997-1998; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1999 FSI Seminar: Correspondence -- Invitations, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 20)